<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-03T09:18:06+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">yellowstroke.com</title><subtitle>Yellowstroke is Budi Tanrim's personal blog, where he jotted down his thoughts, opinions, learnings, and experiments about design.</subtitle><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 self-help information hub</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/15/covid-19/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 self-help information hub" /><published>2020-03-15T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2020-03-15T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/15/covid-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/03/15/covid-19/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A bit context:&lt;/strong&gt;
Hi, I’m not a doctor nor have any scientific background. As I collect information around the world about COVID-19, I thought I share this with an intention to help anyone to be gain information on how to take care yourself, and observe what’s going on with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;where-to-see-the-statistic&quot;&gt;Where to see the statistic?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of site to see the live statistic. You can go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://experience.arcgis.com/experience/685d0ace521648f8a5beeeee1b9125cd&quot;&gt;arcgis website&lt;/a&gt; to see overall statistic in the world, this site pull the data from WHO (World Health Organization)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper medium no-caption&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://experience.arcgis.com/experience/685d0ace521648f8a5beeeee1b9125cd&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-stats.jpg,
    			/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-stats-2x.jpg 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-stats.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Corona Statistic website&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;self-educate&quot;&gt;Self-educate&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source of fear is the unknown. So, here are a few collection of videos that help me understand what actually going on. More will be added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-does-covid-19-mutate&quot;&gt;How does COVID-19 mutate?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;337&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FYPZHA-UjUY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, Dr. John Campbell explained how COVID-19 virus spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;common-questions-answered&quot;&gt;Common questions answered&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;337&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TpXoY_1EG8Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this video, Dr. John Campbell answered a few questions you might have, such as, “Should I be careful when pressing public buttons or use public toilets?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;myth-busters-by-who&quot;&gt;Myth busters by WHO&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check some of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public/myth-busters&quot;&gt;list of myth busters&lt;/a&gt; to help you and people around you not to be confused by un-scientific information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;self-care-and-self-check&quot;&gt;Self-care and self-check&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;washing-hands&quot;&gt;Washing hands&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;337&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1AGW3bbcb3Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many resources says that washing hands is the really effective and crucial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;record-your-own-health-log&quot;&gt;Record your own health-log&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;337&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/fUir2Q1uxxs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to make your health-log and see your condition over time. This is a good resource, probably will help some of you who feel paranoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;will-we-be-immune-once-recovered-from-covid-19&quot;&gt;Will we be immune once recovered from COVID-19?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s still a question whether if a person who recovered from COVID-19 will be immuned or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper medium no-caption&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://thehill.com/changing-america/well-being/prevention-cures/484942-japan-confirms-first-case-of-person-reinfected&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-reinfected.jpg,
    			/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-reinfected-2x.jpg 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-reinfected.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Japan confirms first case of person re-infected&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;keypoints&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Officials in Osaka say a tour bus guide tested positive for COVID-19 for a second time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There have been a number of cases of reinfection in China.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Japan’s prime minister has asked schools to close in an effort to curb the outbreak.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;work-from-home-and-self-quarantine&quot;&gt;Work from home and self-quarantine&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in the room with a lot of people can increases the probability of spreading the virus. So, here are a few good resources to keep your team up and running while work from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper medium no-caption&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/06/health/self-quarantine-coronavirus.html?smid=nytcore-ios-share&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-self-quarantine.jpg,
    			/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-self-quarantine-2x.jpg 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2020/03/covid-19-self-quarantine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The New York Times how to self-quarantine&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;more-to-come-participate-and-suggest-any-good-resources&quot;&gt;More to come: Participate and suggest any good resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would love to hear what good resources you recommend to people. Join this conversation on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/buditanrim/status/1239060277930291200&quot;&gt;Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="workshops," /><category term="meetings" /><summary type="html">A bit context: Hi, I’m not a doctor nor have any scientific background. As I collect information around the world about COVID-19, I thought I share this with an intention to help anyone to be gain information on how to take care yourself, and observe what’s going on with COVID-19.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/covid-19-info-hub.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/covid-19-info-hub.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Workshops can be more efficient than meetings</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/13/workshops-can-be-more-efficient-than-meetings/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workshops can be more efficient than meetings" /><published>2020-02-13T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2020-02-13T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/13/workshops-can-be-more-efficient-than-meetings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/13/workshops-can-be-more-efficient-than-meetings/">&lt;p&gt;Say, your team gets a new project with a challenge to “Design better wayfinding for hospital X”. Things are very abstract and everyone has different opinions. At this point, meetings most likely will be less effective because you’ll need hours of discussion to get alignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest contrast between meetings and workshops is the discussion structure. Meetings require a linear discussion; which means, one person talks, then the other person talks, and so on. Workshops, on the other hand, will be much effective because it allows parallel discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;benefits-of-workshops&quot;&gt;Benefits of workshops&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;parallel-discussion&quot;&gt;Parallel discussion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give everyone post-it and sharpie. Everyone can start writing their opinions or ideas, at the same time. You’ll get very diverse ideas for less than 5 minutes, that otherwise will take more than 30 minutes to discuss all of them in a meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;everyone-has-an-equal-voice&quot;&gt;Everyone has an equal voice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what your title or position in the company, the workshop equalizes the voice level because everyone’s voices represented in the post-it. It’s a great way to avoid the loudest voice in the room to win. Also, give a voice to the silent one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborative-and-real-time-alignment&quot;&gt;Collaborative and real-time alignment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workshops allow everyone to contribute their perspective; questions, ideas, or insights. Imagine, if a designer in your team explores ideas for 2 days alone. Chances are, the exploration can’t be very diverse. Then, your team will hold a meeting to review the designer’s work just to find out the work is not aligned with the product vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if, instead, everyone in the team spends 2 hours doing a brainstorming session? Not only the idea become more diverse. It also allows real-time alignment because everyone agrees and makes a decision together. As a result, your project can move forward faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;guided-conversation&quot;&gt;Guided conversation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike meetings, in workshops, there is a formal facilitator to facilitate the activity. Needless to say, this is beneficial because there’s somebody who really manages the discussion, helps the team understand the agenda, and move the team along until producing the expected output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;feedback-from-real-people&quot;&gt;Feedback from real people&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, In Bukalapak, we started to encourage people to consider workshop format instead of meetings. Here are a few words from people who tried the workshop format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I love we have a rich perspective to solve one big challenge together.”
&lt;cite&gt;Product Manager&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“From this activity, I started to understand what concerns that PM and Designer have. It gives me an opportunity to help and contribute more.”
&lt;cite&gt;Data Scientist&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I wouldn’t imagine if we can come up with all of these ideas. I’m excited to keep doing this in next projects”
&lt;cite&gt;Researcher&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;closing-note&quot;&gt;Closing note&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenge: Workshops require a facilitator&lt;/strong&gt;
Althought workshops can be useful, it has a specific challenge too. It requires someone to facilitate the conversation and have some level of proficiency in a few methods to direct the project. It’s also important that the facilitator come prepared with the agenda to make sure the workshop is effective and achieve the goal. That being said, the workshop can be efficient but it centered on how well the facilitator manages the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nothing wrong with meetings&lt;/strong&gt;
There’s nothing wrong with meetings. Meetings can be a good format when you need to report, monitor the project, or do some work review. But, for some instances when your team needs to make a decision and get things done, the workshop can be a better alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing you want is to sit down for 1-2 hours and end up with nothing other than debates or endless discussion. Share this with your team and start trying 30 minutes or a 1-hour workshop to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think? Are you ready to have an efficient way to collaborate through the workshop?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="workshops," /><category term="meetings" /><summary type="html">Say, your team gets a new project with a challenge to “Design better wayfinding for hospital X”. Things are very abstract and everyone has different opinions. At this point, meetings most likely will be less effective because you’ll need hours of discussion to get alignment.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/workshops-vs-meetings.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/workshops-vs-meetings.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">3 questions designers should be asking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/07/questions-designers-should-ask/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 questions designers should be asking" /><published>2020-02-07T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2020-02-07T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/07/questions-designers-should-ask</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/07/questions-designers-should-ask/">&lt;p&gt;Since our work as a designer is very much in a very abstract phase. We can’t just make a conclusion too soon, because when you do so, your work will be converged too quickly and have a few shortcomings in it. Instead of relying upon conclusion or solution, I usually rely more on the questions because it allows me to constantly reframe my perspective. Here are a couple of questions that I often use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-and-who&quot;&gt;Why and Who&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental question that everyone needs to ask. When things still very abstract in the beginning phase, you can rely on the Why and Who. That must be the center of your focus to help yourself and your team navigates in the abstractness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example of questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why are we even doing this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why are we building this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who will consume this product / experience?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who are our competitors?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A result of this first layer of question is often portrays the high-level objective, strategy, and rationale. It’s a foundation of what you will be working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-might-we&quot;&gt;How might we…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the why and the who get less blurry in the picture of what you do. The how is often time comes up to my mind as a complementary. This question is trying to frame a specific objective that you have in the “why”, but better articulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example of questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How might we reduce the food waste in the hotel buffet?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How might we help an amateur chef to train?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions will frame a problem to a specific point of view based on insights that will prepare your team to start thinking about the “what”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-if&quot;&gt;What if…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presumably, you get a clearer understanding of the why, the who, and the how. At this point, you want to answer those how might we questions and make something a bit more concrete. It’s time to wonder and think as high as a blue sky with “What if…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What if we ask the hotel guest to order the food from the buffet list the night before?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would happen if we make the digital preparation table for the chef?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, we answer the “how” with another set of questions and this is great because we still don’t know what the best solution is. In a question format, nothing set in stone and everything is still can be challenged. Also, allow you and your team to keep wondering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t take this as a linear way of thinking. Sure, Why and Who often come first in mind. But, you must be able to juggle around the layers throughout the progress you make. Gather information as you go and reframe your perspective if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what question do you want to ask next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to have a conversation! Hit me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/buditanrim&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="questions," /><category term="what" /><category term="if," /><category term="why," /><category term="who" /><summary type="html">Since our work as a designer is very much in a very abstract phase. We can’t just make a conclusion too soon, because when you do so, your work will be converged too quickly and have a few shortcomings in it. Instead of relying upon conclusion or solution, I usually rely more on the questions because it allows me to constantly reframe my perspective. Here are a couple of questions that I often use.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/yellowstroke-seo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/yellowstroke-seo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Walking 1on1: A refreshing way to connect</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/walking-1on1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Walking 1on1: A refreshing way to connect" /><published>2020-02-06T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2020-02-06T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/walking-1on1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/02/06/walking-1on1/">&lt;p&gt;When I was in Canada, my favorite things to do is walking from the office back to my home. It’s a refreshing activity to observe my surrounding and reflect to myself after a long hour work and thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After moving back to Indonesia, I missed this right away. In Indonesia, it’s impossible to walk around the city due to the way the culture shaped the city. To be fair, it’s possible to walk around the city to some extend, but it’s a lot of hassle and dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, I read somewhere about the concept of walking 1on1 meeting and actually had it for a few times back in Canada. Yes, basically, you walk while having a conversation. Intrigued about this idea because I can somewhat walk around and refreshed myself from lots of meetings, I’ve done a few of my 1on1 meeting in this format and here are a few things I want to share:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less distraction.&lt;/strong&gt; Sitting down in the room sometimes allow me to be less focused, because I will be distracted with phone or laptop. Walking around will forces us away from the gadget. However, walking can be distracting sometimes if you met somebody and you have to say hi. But, rarely happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More to talk about.&lt;/strong&gt; I believe the more blood circulation happens, the more our brain stimulated? I believe there is a research about this. In my experiment during this week, seems like everyone who I have 1on1 with can talk out their thought continuously. At the end, we have more to talk about in such a short time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More relaxed.&lt;/strong&gt; The advantage about walking 1on1 in Indonesia culture is less eye-contact. I feel like I can focus on the discussion because we walk side by side and less intense eye-contact, which makes things less awkward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-observation&quot;&gt;Small observation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt;. I never tried this with somebody new or someone I haven’t build a trust rapport before. So, not sure about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taking notes?&lt;/strong&gt; This probably drive note-taker people nuts. However, since I was so focused on the conversation, I can almost remember what chunks we talked about. I tried to summarize things before we end our walk and quickly jot down the big themes of our conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper medium photo&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2020/02/1on1-walk-mila.jpg,
    			/img/post/2020/02/1on1-walk-mila-2x.jpg 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2020/02/1on1-walk-mila.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;1on1 walking around office&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Thanks to Dina for silently took the picture. lol&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all. I’d encourage you to try this one. Let me know what you think on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/buditanrim&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="managerial," /><category term="1on1" /><summary type="html">When I was in Canada, my favorite things to do is walking from the office back to my home. It’s a refreshing activity to observe my surrounding and reflect to myself after a long hour work and thinking.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/1on1walk.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/1on1walk.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My hope for stubborn ‘Innovators’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/21/for-stubborn-leaders/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My hope for stubborn 'Innovators'" /><published>2019-11-21T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2019-11-21T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/21/for-stubborn-leaders</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/11/21/for-stubborn-leaders/">&lt;p&gt;Many people confused between ideas with innovation.
Some believe innovation is the idea popped in their heads during dinner or shower. Then, they become really stubborn with that idea. I mean, those can be profound idea for you, but not necessarily what others want. Throughout my career, I’ve witnessed some senior leaderships came to the team and requested random features out of the blue. When they get asked, “Why should we work on this feature?” They will ignorantly answer, “Just do it my way, I know my shit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what happens in that story, right?
If I can simplify, there are 2 possible outcomes from that story.
First, the team might just do it and get “some” results but struggle to make a significant improvement or growth in the future. For me, if it’s a success, it’s just pure luck and not sustainble. The second possibility is the team ship and launch something no one wants to use. Which often time happens. Oops!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often people don’t realize they do that. I mean, even me, as Design Practitioners, can jump to conclusion too soon from time to time. It’s our nature, a default way of thinking. Worse, all the great and success stories from the innovators always talk about one-single-person behind that invention. I think this victimizes our way of thinking to believe that our idea could be one of that success story. Of course, there is that possibility, but in today’s reality where the competition is up high and new startup around the block ready to disrupt the industry, we have to think and work smarter. We can’t hope we do random thing and wish the best luck out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way I see it, innovation is a process to create, offer, and provide a better way of doing something. A better experience for the user to master their environment. Therefore, it’s important to focus on the user’s problem and context first, which often we can get by observing the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-okay-to-have-ideas-but-dont-be-stubborn-and-fixated-about-it&quot;&gt;It’s okay to have ideas, but don’t be stubborn and fixated about it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, it’s okay to have ideas though. Without it, we can’t start any thoughts or conversation. But don’t randomly request a feature and then be stubborn with that specific solution. I can talk about few methods, this and that. Instead, here’s a simple suggestion for leaders who often give a random feature request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;distill-it-down-from-feature-to-problem&quot;&gt;Distill it down from feature to problem&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come to your team and say, &lt;strong&gt;“Hey, I think this __ feature will be useful because it can solve ____ problem. Can we brainstorm and explore other possibilities to solve this problem?”&lt;/strong&gt;
Talk about that specific solution with an open mindset. Talk about what problem you want to solve. The priority should be solving that problem, not your solution! Give space for your team can uncover that problem and opportunity and then ideate together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;talk-about-the-expected-user-outcome-of-that-feature&quot;&gt;Talk about the expected user outcome of that feature&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come to the team and talk about, &lt;strong&gt;“Hey, I have this ____ idea, I believe it can help our user to do _____ (better experience). I wonder if there’s a better idea to help our user achieve experience?”&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t be stubborn about the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, Experience Designer and Design Researcher will be your best friend to help you get to observe your users and understand their pain points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-be-stubborn-stupid&quot;&gt;Don’t be stubborn, stupid.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Focus on the problem and be open for other solutions. Because, at the end, if you truly are an innovators, you should be passionated about solving that problem to empower your user to live their life easier and better. Plus, by doing that, you company could gain a better business outcome later on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="mindset," /><category term="leadership" /><summary type="html">Many people confused between ideas with innovation. Some believe innovation is the idea popped in their heads during dinner or shower. Then, they become really stubborn with that idea. I mean, those can be profound idea for you, but not necessarily what others want. Throughout my career, I’ve witnessed some senior leaderships came to the team and requested random features out of the blue. When they get asked, “Why should we work on this feature?” They will ignorantly answer, “Just do it my way, I know my shit.”</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/x.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/x.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Five simple actions to help you gain more time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/18/protect-your-time/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five simple actions to help you gain more time" /><published>2019-07-18T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2019-07-18T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/07/18/protect-your-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/07/18/protect-your-time/">&lt;p&gt;No matter where you work; big company, startup company, or self-employed. I think we’re all agree that time is such a precious and important aspect of ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, very often people hesitance to say no to a meeting invitation. Before they knew it, their calendar gets cramped and complained about how they don’t have enough time to either do the work or think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re in this situation, look at your calendar and try to do these five actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-eliminate&quot;&gt;1. Eliminate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-there-any-recurring-meeting-that-you-can-let-go&quot;&gt;Is there any recurring meeting that you can let go?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of us have a recurring meeting, either it’s bi-weekly or weekly meeting. In the beginning, maybe the intention is good. But after a while, that recurring meeting often becomes less efficient due to the nature of your team dynamic or project dynamic. The idea is to identify those and ask if it is  worth to take everyone’s time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-loosen-up&quot;&gt;2. Loosen up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-there-any-weekly-meeting-that-you-can-loosen-up-to-bi-weekly&quot;&gt;Is there any weekly meeting that you can loosen up to bi-weekly?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to see if you really need those weekly meeting. Gauge how important to those meetings based on your current priorities. See which meetings you can loosen up to bi-weekly so you can have more time to work or focus on other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-reduce&quot;&gt;3. Reduce&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;can-you-reduce-any-meeting-down-to-30-or-45-minutes&quot;&gt;Can you reduce any meeting down to 30 or 45 minutes?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have 2 hours meeting, that’s probably not gonna be super-efficient. Realistically, do you need those 2 hours to resolve the issue? Most of the time, I witnessed people spend hours of meeting just to discuss something they can resolve via chat or email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-re-arrange&quot;&gt;4. Re-arrange&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-there-any-meeting-you-can-stack-together-to-give-yourself-more-time-collectively&quot;&gt;Is there any meeting you can stack together to give yourself more time collectively?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last thing you can do is to re-arrange a few meetings. Just by doing that, you can have a better window of time. So, say here’s how your schedule looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.00-1.30 PM (30 minutes of meeting)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.30-2.30 PM (1 hour of working time)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.30-3.30 PM (1 hour of meeting)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3.30-5.00 PM (2 hours of working time)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If possible, re-arrange those 2.30-3.30 PM meeting. Say, we can re-arrange it to 1.30. Then, you’ll have 3 hours as a window of time to work. It’s just better to reduce the context-switching over and over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-prioritize&quot;&gt;5. Prioritize&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, hopefully, you have more time after doing those 4 actions above. Now, ask yourself, if you have more time in this world, what would you want to focus? Pick one or two per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a balancing act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you can’t just ignore all the meetings or reduce them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These may look simple but often forgotten because of that.
Time is precious, be conscious about it. Work hard is good, but work smart is better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><summary type="html">No matter where you work; big company, startup company, or self-employed. I think we’re all agree that time is such a precious and important aspect of ours.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/yellowstroke-seo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/yellowstroke-seo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Evolving Product Experience Principles at Bukalapak</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/04/23/evolving-bukalapak-principles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Evolving Product Experience Principles at Bukalapak" /><published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/23/evolving-bukalapak-principles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/04/23/evolving-bukalapak-principles/">&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper medium&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2019/04/bukalapak-principles.jpg,
    			/img/post/2019/04/bukalapak-principles-2x.jpg 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2019/04/bukalapak-principles.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;alt&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On my second month at Bukalapak, we started having a discussion about evolving our Design Principles. After a few months working and advocating for it. I had a chance to share it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/bukalapakproductdesign/evolving-product-design-principles-at-bukalapak-366ab45ae5a6?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=188effec06bb832a6bd429d669d65bda&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;. On that post, I shared some of the key highlights that I think are worth sharing, a bit of the process, and how we managed to keep things on track by having a certain criteria for “good” principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and give &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/bukalapakproductdesign/evolving-product-design-principles-at-bukalapak-366ab45ae5a6?source=friends_link&amp;amp;sk=188effec06bb832a6bd429d669d65bda&quot;&gt;it a read&lt;/a&gt;. I hope you enjoy them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="principles," /><category term="philosophy," /><category term="collaboration" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/bukalapak-principles-seo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/bukalapak-principles-seo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A framework to give better design feedback: Analyze, Discuss, Suggest</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/09/a-framework-to-give-better-design-feedback/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A framework to give better design feedback: Analyze, Discuss, Suggest" /><published>2019-03-09T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2019-03-09T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/03/09/a-framework-to-give-better-design-feedback</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/03/09/a-framework-to-give-better-design-feedback/">&lt;p&gt;Feedback is a gift. Feedback has a vital role in product development. Not only it can nurture the product, but it also could nurture the people who build the product. Yet as we’re all know, giving good constructive feedback is damn hard. Hence, I have been experimenting with this framework to make myself better at it; which hopefully can be useful for you too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-framework&quot;&gt;The framework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;analyze-discuss-and-suggest&quot;&gt;Analyze, Discuss, and Suggest&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This framework helps me navigate when I’m reviewing works. I’ll explain a little bit of each point and guiding principles on each. Let’s dig into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper illustration small&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/eyes.gif,
    			/img/post/2019/03/eyes-2x.gif 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/eyes.gif&quot; alt=&quot;analyze&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;analyze&quot;&gt;Analyze&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you’ll need to do is to listen and analyze the work. What I mean here is to see if anything stand out from work presented, which can be both good things and bad things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few things to keep in mind:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First thing first, the intent of the feedback should always &lt;em&gt;be helpful&lt;/em&gt; and not be offensive nor destructive. &lt;em&gt;Be respectful&lt;/em&gt; to the team presenting. Sure, you can analyze everything, but if the presenter asks for specific feedback, you should respect that and make that as a priority. Also, &lt;em&gt;be sincere,&lt;/em&gt; it’s not quite useful to give any insincere compliment (like sandwich method) and focus on what matters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you spot something that doesn’t feel right, pay attention to that and try to complete the blank of this statement: “I’m not sure about X because…”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few questions that I’ll try to answer while analyzing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the goal of this project?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What human problem is this trying to solve?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How close is this design achieve the goal?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do I feel about this in general?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper illustration small&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/chat-bubble.gif,
    			/img/post/2019/03/chat-bubble-2x.gif 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/chat-bubble.gif&quot; alt=&quot;discuss&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discuss&quot;&gt;Discuss&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s the time to discuss what you’ve analyzed. Whenever possible, try to spark the conversation around the room rather than giving a statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few things I’d pay attention at this point:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now, let’s say the work presented is 180-degrees from where you think it needs to be or maybe there’s an &lt;em&gt;aha&lt;/em&gt;-idea in your head. Well, hold on. Ask questions first, &lt;em&gt;try to understand&lt;/em&gt; why the team did that in the first place. Maybe the team has thought about that and have a rationale on why not to pursue that idea. And most importantly, &lt;em&gt;do not dominate&lt;/em&gt; the conversation so you can learn and read the room better, this can be a good opportunity to do a gut check.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper illustration small&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/pencil.gif,
    			/img/post/2019/03/pencil-2x.gif 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/pencil.gif&quot; alt=&quot;discuss&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;suggest&quot;&gt;Suggest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you analyze and discuss, it could be helpful to suggest a sort of direction or guidance. This part often blends together with the discussion. And, by the way, this doesn’t mean you always have to give a suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A few things I’d pay attention at this point:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When suggesting a direction, try to make it &lt;em&gt;solution-agnostic,&lt;/em&gt; which mean the suggestion should not imply any sort of specific solution because you want to give a room for the team to explore. At the same time, you have to &lt;em&gt;be articulate,&lt;/em&gt; you have to be clear on what you think needs to be improved. Otherwise, it will be very hard for anyone to know what do they need to improve upon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the discussion started, things can get pretty messy. Maybe some people in the room start to raise different philosophies or opinions about which direction to take, which is normal. When it happens, what I find useful is to lay out all the options on the table and this can be helpful for the team or the decision maker to weigh on what’s the best direction moving forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;additional-note&quot;&gt;Additional note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-dont-feel-great-about-the-last-feedback-session-i-had-what-should-i-do&quot;&gt;I don’t feel great about the last feedback session I had, what should I do?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry, we’re all been there! Try again. With this framework, you can analyze which part you are at the most? It’s all about the balanced seasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyze 20%, Discuss 10%, Suggest 70% = Possibly destructive&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
If you spend more time suggesting your thought, that can lead to destructive feedback because you spend a lot of time articulating your thought without trying to understand the context or the situation of that team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analyze 30%, Discuss 60%, Suggest 10% = Somewhat balance&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
This is the combination that I’d prefer. If you spend more time to discuss and understand, chances are, you will be able to help the team in the area they struggle with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sometimes-i-suggest-a-solution-is-it-a-bad-thing&quot;&gt;Sometimes, I suggest a solution, is it a bad thing?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I’ll try to avoid that. Sometimes, I do that too when I’m running out of time or maybe I’m running out of patience. But, this shouldn’t happen often. Giving a solution-agnostic suggestion is healthier for the team because it will let them go through the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-chat-to-the-reader&quot;&gt;Closing chat to the reader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this is useful. You can try it, maybe experiment with it a little bit. I’d love to hear if you have another framework, or maybe you have questions – you know you can &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:buditanrim@gmail.com?subject=Question&quot;&gt;reach me out&lt;/a&gt;. And as always, if you think the post is worth sharing, share it with your friends, colleagues, or (maybe) the rest of the world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper illustration small&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/cover-yellowstroke-framework-feedback.gif,
    			/img/post/2019/03/cover-yellowstroke-framework-feedback-2x.gif 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2019/03/cover-yellowstroke-framework-feedback.gif&quot; alt=&quot;analyze&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><category term="feedback," /><category term="discussion," /><category term="framework" /><summary type="html">Feedback is a gift. Feedback has a vital role in product development. Not only it can nurture the product, but it also could nurture the people who build the product. Yet as we’re all know, giving good constructive feedback is damn hard. Hence, I have been experimenting with this framework to make myself better at it; which hopefully can be useful for you too.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/feedback-framework-seo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/feedback-framework-seo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Making a decision is hard, here’s my rule of thumb</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/28/rule-of-thumb-for-making-a-decision/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making a decision is hard, here's my rule of thumb" /><published>2019-01-28T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2019-01-28T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/28/rule-of-thumb-for-making-a-decision</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/28/rule-of-thumb-for-making-a-decision/">&lt;p&gt;Starting my new role as a Principal Designer, I see myself in a lot of situation where I need to make important decisions. I can tell you that it’s not always easy, sometimes I’m worried if I’ll make a bad decision. Derive from this worry, I started to look for a rule of thumb when considering different options and I want to share where I’m at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-coin-has-two-sides&quot;&gt;A coin has two sides&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last weekend, while enjoying my slow Saturday morning, my eyes caught a coin on a table. As I picked it up, I started to remember this saying about every coin has two sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see, a coin has two different sides, known as head and tail. Similarly to decision making, there are two sides to each decision. No matter what, it always has its upside and the downside. For me, this is a simple framework to use when I’m facing several options and not sure which one you should take. Using this simple rule of thumb remind me of every side of each decision and think it thorougly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img-wrapper illustration medium&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img srcset=&quot;/img/post/2019/01/two-coin.jpg,
    			/img/post/2019/01/two-coin-2x.jpg 2x&quot; src=&quot;/img/post/2019/01/two-coin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Two sides of coin yellowstroke&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Head and tail(?)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-coin-has-its-third-side-if-you-observe-it-long-enough&quot;&gt;A coin has its third side if you observe it long enough&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you hold the coin flat toward you, you’ll see the very thin part in between the head and the tail. That’s the third side, which might be hard to recognize in the beginning. But it’s there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to the decision thing. Once you have the upside and the downside, remember there’s no one perfect answer. It always depends on this third factor; which decision benefit you the most with your certain need, goal, condition, and context. Therefore, when making a decision, find the obvious upside and downside. Then find the third factor to help you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><summary type="html">Starting my new role as a Principal Designer, I see myself in a lot of situation where I need to make important decisions. I can tell you that it’s not always easy, sometimes I’m worried if I’ll make a bad decision. Derive from this worry, I started to look for a rule of thumb when considering different options and I want to share where I’m at.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/two-coins.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/two-coins.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Essential skills for Product Designers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/04/essential-skills-for-designer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Essential skills for Product Designers" /><published>2018-12-04T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2018-12-04T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/12/04/essential-skills-for-designer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/12/04/essential-skills-for-designer/">&lt;p&gt;Product designers are solving complex problems these days. We’re working every day to understand the users, the problems and trying to come up with a solution that we iterate over time. But, what does it take to be a good one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I have invited a few friends of mine to pick their brains and wisdom. So, I poked a few of them and ask them a cliché question: &lt;em&gt;If you can pick one, what is the most important skill to have as a Product Designer?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s hear what they have to say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;bill-empathy-baked-into-communication&quot;&gt;Bill: “Empathy baked into communication.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Communication is the secret sauce. And not just that. Empathy baked into communication. A designer can have all the raw talent in the world but without great communication, they fall short of the bigger picture. Why, you say? Well, part of designing for a client is also selling your work. You do that by telling a story, communicating your thoughts and ideas in a compelling way. Communicating. After a certain phase in your career, no longer can you just wow people with pretty visuals. They need the why. They need solid communication.&lt;br /&gt;
What happens when the clients start to lose faith as you explore endlessly to please them. What happens when times get hard. Communication is just about all that will solve this. Throw some empathy in there and you are now making headway. Clients often need to be heard, understood, and comforted. Queue up good communication skills and you have a MUCH better chance at navigating the harder waters.&lt;br /&gt;
Communication helps from start to end. Setting expectations, describing your needs, sharing your insights, etc. Get your communication skills down and you are really set up for success!
 &lt;cite&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/billskenney&quot;&gt;Bill S. Kenney&lt;/a&gt;, Co-Founder of &lt;a href=&quot;https://focuslabllc.com/&quot;&gt;Focuslab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;bady-endurance-is-rare&quot;&gt;Bady: “Endurance is rare.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’d say it would be Grit. I think It’s not only about talent, or passion but also being able to stay focus on your end goal in a long shot. If you want to make some changes in the industry that has been around for centuries, it will require a good amount of effort and patient. Passion/enthusiasm is common but endurance/patient is rare.
&lt;cite&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/bady&quot;&gt;Bady QB&lt;/a&gt;, Design Lead at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dbs.com/design&quot;&gt;DBS Bank&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;david-listen&quot;&gt;David: “Listen.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you receive a new project, listen to your manager. Ask for requirements, historical information, the definition of done, timelines, etc.
When you show your designs, listen to your design team. Ask follow-up questions. Consider every piece of feedback even if you disagree with it. Try their suggestions. Make a few more iterations. 
When you show your prototypes, listen to your users. They will surprise you by interpreting interfaces in ways you did not expect. Ask why. Ask what they’re thinking. Ask what they expected.&lt;br /&gt;
When you hear concerns and clarifications, listen to your engineers. They need to solve problems you most likely didn’t consider. If they have a tough sprint they may need to find ways to simplify your proposal. Cooperation and compromise are key to building strong relationships.
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freshlyground.design&quot;&gt;David Klein&lt;/a&gt;, Lead Product Designer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salesforce.com&quot;&gt;Salesforce&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;scott-make-sure-nothing-gets-interpreted-differently-than-how-i-intended&quot;&gt;Scott: “Make sure nothing gets interpreted differently than how I intended.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Making sure the other people understand your ideas exactly as you do. A lot of times when talking to designers you just assume the other person knows what you’re thinking. Unfortunately, this isn’t always true. The more complex the problems and solutions are, the more ways someone can incorrectly interpret what you’re proposing. This issue is even trickier working for a remote company like InVision. Making sure people understand your ideas requires an extra layer of communication and choosing the right medium to share your work through. I try not to share static mockups or links to prototypes that people can use as there’s always a lack of context to the problem you’re trying to solve or how exactly your solution will work. Instead, I usually create high-fidelity prototypes and do a screen recording of me using it while I explain things overtop. I find this gives me the chance to make sure nothing gets interpreted differently than how I intended.
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scottsavarie&quot;&gt;Scott Savarie&lt;/a&gt;, Principal Product Designer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://invisionapp.com/studio&quot;&gt;InVision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;russell-able-to-take-multiple-opposing-pieces-of-feedback&quot;&gt;Russell: “Able to take multiple opposing pieces of feedback.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the things I’ve learned as a designer, is that the more experience you have, the more you are able to take multiple opposing pieces of feedback, whether it be constraints, or objectives of the project, and find a way to design a solution that reconciles all of them.
For example, a user experience stakeholder might say that this experience should feel snappy and quick, where another technical stakeholder might say that although they’d like that to be possible, they are heavily constrained, and so technical performance will be limited. Initially it sounds like both groups can’t get what they want, but I think a skilled designer embraces the constraints and objectives, and finds a way to make both of those things happen.
This is not to say that this will always be possible, and it’s crucial to weigh the importance of those pieces of feedback, to make sure you are making the right tradeoffs, but by embracing an opposable mind, you can often achieve much more than what you initially thought possible.
Take those two opposing thoughts and put them against each other. Ask yourself, how might we enable a snappy experience, while we are technically constrained? By opening your mind to what you want to be true, and not focusing on what’s not possible, you can find so much more.
One of my favourite books that explains this idea of opposable ideas, and the opposable mind in general, is &lt;em&gt;A Technique For Producing Ideas by James Webb Young.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://imrusty.com/&quot;&gt;Russell Baylis&lt;/a&gt;, Senior Designer at &lt;a href=&quot;https://shopify.com&quot;&gt;Shopify&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;aleš-communication-is-necessary-skills-if-you-want-to-be-a-professional&quot;&gt;Aleš: “Communication is necessary skills if you want to be a professional.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’d say it is communication and presentation skills. Straight-up. Besides doing good work you also need to know how to talk about it with confidence. It is important to learn how to explain your ideas, solutions, and decisions. Because only then you can bring other people on board. I always use a simple rule for this: you can do the best work of your life, but if you can’t explain it to your client, colleague or manager, it’s going to be useless and you’re never going to make it into a final product.
Communication can be hard and be uncomfortable, especially for introverts (including myself), but it is necessary skills if you want to be a professional. If you master it or get better at least, it can really do wonders for you.
 &lt;cite&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/alesnesetril&quot;&gt;Aleš Nešetřil&lt;/a&gt;, Creative Director at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.strv.com/&quot;&gt; STRV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;spacing-extra-loose&quot; id=&quot;mason-a-unique-point-of-view-is-crucial-born&quot;&gt;Mason: “A unique point of view is crucial-born.”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;interview&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The most important skill a designer should possess is a strong point of view and look for this in every designer with whom I collaborate. While the technical or mechanical aspects of design can be mimicked, a unique point of view is crucial—born from a solid understanding of design fundamentals, good common sense and years of practice. With a strong perspective, your work with stand out from the crowd and people will take notice.&lt;br /&gt;
Some examples of designers who possess this? In Mixpanel’s case, I began consulting with them when they were in their infancy. Eventually, I officially joined the team and after the first year, it was the perfect time to add another designer. I had collaborated with Julien Renvoye on a few freelance projects and we kept in touch quite a bit. Julien has always had a voracious appetite for good design. He’s the kind of designer that puts so much love in every project that it compels me to keep pushing boundaries and improve my skills. What drew me to his work from the start was his unique perspective found in every project. There was always a level of polish that few designers achieve. He was the second designer that Mixpanel hired.
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/yarnell&quot;&gt;Mason Yarnell&lt;/a&gt;, Previously Design Lead at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mixpanel.com/&quot;&gt; Mixpanel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-closing-chat-with-the-reader&quot;&gt;A closing chat with the reader&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aren’t these great? While it is not realistic to live with solely one skill, I hope this gives you different lenses about what important for Product Designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people tend to focus on the hard-skills and forget about the soft-skills. After talking to a few fellow designers, I couldn’t agree more. The communication and collaboration is often the top pick. If I may add though, I’d say the ability to articulate the design decision is also important because it’s a result of the combination of having an ability to understand of the problem in depth and the communication skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step up your soft skills, be more aware of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Budi Tanrim</name></author><summary type="html">Product designers are solving complex problems these days. We’re working every day to understand the users, the problems and trying to come up with a solution that we iterate over time. But, what does it take to be a good one?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/yellowstroke-seo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/img/seo/yellowstroke-seo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>